The Sturgis-Tappan Family Papers, 1812-1982
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Sturgis-Tappan family papers
1812-1982
Sturgis-Tappan Family
MS 186
4 boxes (1.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Authors and Poets. Approximately two thirds of material is correspondence and the rest is writings and drawings. Includes pencil drawings and watercolors, drafts of poems, and one published volume. Some biographical material.
William Sturgis was born 25 February 1782, the son of William Sturgis and Hannah Mills. He was a prominent Boston merchant and co-founder of Bryant and Sturgis, and made his fortune in the China Trade. He married Elizabeth Marston Davis and they had six children, among them two daughters, Ellen (1812-1848) and Caroline (1819-1888). Caroline Sturgis married William Aspinwall Tappan, son of Lewis Tappan, a noted abolitionist, and Susanna Aspinwall; they had two children, Ellen Sturgis Tappan and Mary Aspinwall Tappan. Caroline Sturgis Tappan and her sister, Ellen Sturgis Hooper, were minor Transcendentalist poets whose work was occasionally published in the Dial. They counted among their acquaintances William Ellery Channing, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Henry James, and Henry David Thoreau. The sisters, especially Caroline, were also friendly with Margaret Fuller and regularly attended her celebrated "conversations," begun in 1839.
The Tappans lived in Boston and summered in the Berkshire Mountains of Western Massachusetts. In 1936, Mary Aspinwall Tappan and her niece, Rosamond Sturgis Dixey Brooks (Caroline Sturgis Tappan's granddaughter), gave the family's summer estate, Tanglewood, to the Boston Symphony Orchestra.
The Sturgis-Tappan Papers consist of 1.25 linear feet dating from 1812 to 1983, approximately two thirds of which is correspondence and the rest of which is writings and drawings. Types of material include correspondence, pencil drawings and watercolors, drafts of poems, and one published volume.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Writings and Drawings
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection. Original letters by Ralph Waldo Emerson are in a secure location in the Sophia Smith Collection; photocopies for normal use are in the Sturgis-Tappan Family Papers, although researchers may request special permission to examine the originals.
History of the Collection
Daphne Brooks Prout donated the Sturgis-Tappan Family Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1983 and 1985.
Search Terms
Channing, William Ellery, 1780-1842--Correspondence; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882--Correspondence; Fuller, Margaret, 1810-1850; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864--Correspondence; Hawthorne, Sophia Peabody, 1809-1871--Correspondence; Hooper, Ellen Sturgis, 1812-1848; Tappan, Mary Aspinwall, 1851-; Tappan, Caroline Sturgis, 1819-1888; James, William--Correspondence; Tappan family; Sturgis family; Tanglewood Music Center--History; Authors, American--19th century; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Family--United States--19th century--History--Sources; New England--Intellectual life--19th century; Women poets, American--19th century; Transcendentalists (New England)
Additional Information
Related Material
Caroline Sturgis Tappan's collection of travel photographs is located in the Smith College Art Museum, and material pertaining to Tanglewood may be found in the Boston Symphony Orchestra Archives
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1836-1982, .25 linear ft.
  This series consists of information about members of the Sturgis-Tappan Family (primarily photocopied excerpts from various reference books and anthologies); a photograph of Caroline Sturgis Tappan and a published catalog about her Grand Tour of Europe; and correspondence pertaining to the transfer of Tanglewood to the Boston Symphony Orchestra.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1812-1913, .75 linear ft.
  This series is the largest in the collection and is organized into three subseries: letters to and from Caroline Sturgis Tappan, letters to and from her daughter, Mary Aspinwall Tappan, and third party correspondence. The correspondence is extensive among family members across three generations. Also included are letters to and from Lydia Maria Child, William Ellery Channing, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Sophia Hawthorne, and William James. (The Emerson correspondence is significant, while that of the others here listed is limited to one or two letters.)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND DRAWINGS 1849-59, .25 linear ft.
  This series contains primarily pencil drawings and watercolor sketches by Caroline Sturgis Tappan, as well as drafts of poems attributed to Tappan and to her sister, Ellen Sturgis Hooper. There is also correspondence pertaining to ownership of plates for Rainbows for Children (1848), a book by Lydia Maria Child.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL 1836-1982
  - Family history
    - Photocopies of pages from various books, 1914, 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The American Transcendentalists: Their Prose and Poetry (1957) and The Transcendentalists: An Anthology 1950 by Perry Miller: photocopies of excerpts, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes taken on the Tappan family by George McCandlish: photocopies, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Caroline Sturgis Tappan and the Grand Tour by George Dimock (2 copies), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Account of Lewis Henry Tappan's first two years (brother of William Aspinwall Tappan), by his father, Lewis Tappan, circa 1823 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      [See Oversize Materials]
  - Caroline Sturgis Tappan: photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tanglewood: correspondence, 1836-56, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1812-1913
  - Caroline Sturgis Tappan
    - Family
      - Bigelow, William S., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Dixey, Ellen Sturgis Tappan, 1875-87 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
      - Dixey, Richard Cowell, 1875-85 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Goodwin, Ezra, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Hooper, Anne Sturgis, 1855-59, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
      - Hooper, Edward W., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Sturgis, Susan, 1849, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Sturgis, William, 1848-50 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Tappan, Lewis (combined letter from Caroline Sturgis Tappan and Ellen Sturgis Tappan (Dixey) [father-in-law/grandfather, respectively], 1861 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Tappan, Mary Aspinwall, 1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified relative, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Friends and acquaintances
      - Channing, William Ellery, n.d (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Child, Lydia Maria, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        [See also Oversize Materials]
      - Emerson, Ralph Waldo (includes some photocopies), 1838-72, undated (Box 1, Folder 24-35)
      - Hawthorne, Sophia, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - James, William, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - White, Ellen, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Mary Aspinwall Tappan
    - Family
      - General, 1887, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Bigelow, William S. 1888, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Brooks, Gorham, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Dixey, Arthur Sturgis, 1890-1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
      - Dixey, Ellen Sturgis Tappan, 1879-1910 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
      - Dixey, Rosamond Sturgis, 1908-24 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Tappan, William Aspinwall, 1886-1904, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Friends and acquaintances
      - James, William, 1901, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1905-32 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Other family members
    - Bigelow, William S. to family, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Davis, John to William W. Sturgis, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Dixey, Ellen Sturgis Tappan to various recipients, 1851-95 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Dixey, Richard W. to wife, Rebecca Dixey, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hooper, Anne Sturgis to various recipients, 1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Hooper, Ellen Sturgis to William Swain, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sturgis, Ellen M. to Ellen Goodwin, 1815-25 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sturgis, Susan to William Swain, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Sturgis, William to various recipients, 1812-59 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sturgis, William W. to various recipients, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Tappan, Susan A. to "Mrs. Colonel Aspinwall" (sister), 1821 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Tappan, William Aspinwall to various recipients, 1855-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Third party
    - Emerson, Ralph Waldo
      - Forbes, Margaret, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Tappan, William Aspinwall (photocopies), 1845, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Payne, Eloisa, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND DRAWINGS 1849-59
  - Drawings: Tappan, Caroline Sturgis
    - Pencil sketches, 1846-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Pencil sketches and watercolor paintings: album, undated (Box 3)
      [Located in Box 4]
  - Poetry
    - Tappan, Caroline Sturgis: handwritten booklet of poetry with pressed flowers, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Tappan, Caroline Sturgis and Ellen Sturgis Hooper (?): miscellaneous poems, 1836, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "G.W.": "Nebulae," undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified author: handwritten book of poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence pertaining to Rainbows for Children by Lydia Maria Child, 1849-59 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Published etchings by various artists of sites in Great Britain, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Album of pencil sketches and watercolor paintings by Caroline Sturgis Tappan, undated (Box 4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Letter to Mary Aspinwall Tappan from Arthur Sturgis Dixey, 29 Nov 1894 (?) (Map-case Flat file)